Guide to the Artifacts and Relics Collection, 1830s-[ongoing]
Duke University. University Archives
Artifacts and Relics collection 1830s-[ongoing]
Duke University. University Archives
70.2 linear feet Extent: about 257 Items
Artifacts, memorabilia, pins, awards, textiles, and other materials, either related to or produced by Trinity College and Duke University or collected by Trinity College Historical Society or other offices and individuals as historical curiosities.
uaartrel
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Artifacts and Relics Collection were received by the University Archives as both gifts and transfers.
Collection Overview
Artifacts, memorabilia, pins, awards, textiles, and other materials, either related to or produced by Trinity College and Duke University or collected by Trinity College Historical Society or other offices and individuals as historical curiosities. Includes academic apparel from university leaders, athletic memorabilia, commemorative plates, and shoulder patches from the Armed Forces units that Duke alumni served in.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Trinity College Historical Society; Armed Forces -- Medals, badges, decorations, etc; Duke University -- Awards; Duke University -- Artifacts; Duke University -- Memorabilia; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.)--Awards; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.)--Artifacts; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.)--Memorabilia; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Awards; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Artifacts; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Memorabilia
Related Material
Trinity College Historical Society Collection
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Items stored in slots (Box 1)
    - Slot 1: Duke University Service pin, 10 years
    - Slot 2: Hesperian Literary Society Orators medal, 1851; to: T.A. Smoot, Trinity College, 1851
    - Slot 3: Demosthenes Aeschines medal 1851 (debating); to: T.A. Smoot
    - Slot 4: Trinity College ring, Class of 1917 with yellow ribbon (from Exie Duncan)
    - Slot 5: Lapel pin with Duke Family Crest, from opening of Washington Duke Inn and Golf Club, December 9, 1988
    - Slot 6: Duke University Service pin, 30 years (donor: Exie Duncan)
    - Slot 7: Columbian Literary Society medal, Trinity College senior class, 1876, C.F. Tanner
    - Slot 8: Columbian Literary Society medal, Trinity College, Praemuim Disputationi, 1893, Plummer Stewart (UA83-3)
    - Slot 9: Columbian Literary Society medal Trinity College, senior class, 1894, Plummer Stewart (UA83-3)
    - Slot 10: Columbian Literary Society medal Trinity College, Praemium Oratori, 1894, Plummer Stewart (UA83-3)
    - Slot 11: N.C. Teachers Assembly Oratory, 1894, Plummer Stewart (UA83-3)
    - Slot 12: Hesperian Literary Society, Normal College pin, 1851
    - Slot 13: Phi Beta Kappa key, Trinity College, 1924, Nora Chaffin
    - Slot 14: Hesperian Literary Society, Trinity College Orators medal, 1895, Thomas A. Smoot
    - Slot 15: Hesperian Literary Society, Trinity College pin, 1851
    - Slot 16: Columbian Literary Society, Trinity College, Orators Medal, 1910, Thomas Wilkinson and Millsaps medal for declamation, 1905 Thomas Wilkinson (UA95-117)
    - Slot 17: Piece of brick wall from Divinity School expansion, packaged as a souvenir for Divinity School alumni (James Cannon, dean)
    - Slot 18: Two Terry Sanford for President campaign buttons from 1976 election (from James Henderson)
    - Slot 19: Class of 1929 ring, Martha Layton (UA98-24)
    - Slot 20: Trinity College belt buckle
    - Loose in Box: two illustrated price lists for medals and society pins
  - Bandage, 1940s; prepared by Woman's College students during WWII (Box 2)
  - Framed certificate for $58 million dollars to Duke University for the construction of Duke North Hospital along with the pen used by President Sanford to sign the agreement, 1976
  - Trinity College football patch from Evette Zells, 1978
  - Glass ashtray with Duke University seal
  - Fiftieth anniversary of Duke University, 1924-1974, Ceramic ashtray
  - Duke University Golden anniversary tile, 1974
  - Duke University belt buckle
  - Glass paperweight with image of the Trinity College Library
  - Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory Extra Sensory Perception (ESP) testing cards (3 packs)
  - Trinity College matchbox (metal with image of three men with beer steins, from George W. Jackson, Class of 1923 (UA90-73)
  - Gavel made from the wood from the tree under which Washington Duke was "converted" in 1830; donated by William K. Quick, Founders' Day, December 13, 1981 (explanatory note with gavel)
  - President John Kilgo's Gavel (UA2002-50)
  - Woman's College Class gavel (2)
  - Duke University Class gavel (2)
  - Unidentified gavel (2)
  - Hesperian Literary Society medal, Trinity College, 1875, R.H. Palmer (UA93-13) (Box 3)
  - Carillon tapes, 1939
  - Trinity College, Durham, N.C. commemorative spoon depicting the Trinity gate and the Washington Duke building
  - Pens used at the December 29, 1924 Board of Trustees meeting approving the change of Trinity College to Duke University
  - Freshman bow, class of 1954 (UA94-119)
  - Wakeman Award, designed by John Furlow and Elon Clark
  - Trinity College Football pendant, 1921 - engraved Trinity 17, Wake Forest 0, H.A. Crute, FB
  - Dink, Class of 1953
  - Duke's Mixture, Smoking tobacco, 1 packet
  - Box containing two pendants, TKA key and College Trinity pendant with J.H. Grigg on back; FCTA Sigma Chi pin and Tombs pin
  - Rubber stamp with signature of President William Few
  - Duke All American Bowl button (3)
  - Duke 1989 Final Four pin
  - Celebrating 30 years of Final Fours pin, 1963-1992
  - Student appreciation week pin
  - Clay ball with inscription: Taken from Auditorium, Oct. 5, 1929
  - "A la gloire des Diables Bleus," lapel pin (UA2001-73)
  - Sarah P. Duke Gardens Doris Duke Center ornament (UA2001-93)
  - West Campus Recreation and Fitness Facility Frisbee (UA97-29)
  - Lilly Library frisbee, 1993
  - Lilly Library boxer shorts (UA2004-22)
  - Duke buttons with ribbons (2); Class of 1948 dink; 1948 patch of the Duke seal (UA2005-0088) (Box 4)
  - Duke button with ribbon; leather belt with Duke University belt buckle (UA2007-63)
  - 2001 National Champs T-shirt (Box 5)
  - 2000 Last day of classes T-shirt (UA2001-71)
  - 1999 Final Four T-shirt (UA99-21)
  - Hideaway bar T-shirt
  - Beta Omega Sigma ribbon, 1938 (UA2000-22)
  - 50th anniversary plate; from Charles A. Long, June 1974
  - Class of 1954 dink from Morgan Brenner (UA2009-0008)
  - Duke University Marching Band (DUMB) vest (UA2005-0003) (Box 6)
  - Mortar boards (2)
  - Wooden Trinity seal with J.F.B. '96 on back
  - Pete Ferettini trowels, 1927-1930 (2) (UA97-44) (Box 7)
  - Duke buttons, beads, car banner, snow globe, sun glasses, basketball ticket stub collected 2001-2003 (UA2005-44)
  - Trinity Sweater (UA94-41) (Box 8)
  - Trinity Baseball uniform (UA94-41) (Box 9)
  - T-shirts, from various sports events including a 1981 Banks and Dennard T-shirt (UA94-41) (Box 10)
  - T-shirts, including Women's Studies and 1994 Pan-Africa T-shirt (Box 11)
  - Trinity banners (3)
  - Basketball championship, 1991, 1992, 2001 - pennants, buttons, and T-shirts (Box 12)
  - Two Phi Kappa Psi mini mugs (UA2001-11) (Box 13)
  - Bag with oriental pottery (UA2001-11)
  - September 8, 1984 Wallace Wade Stadium button (UA2001-11)
  - Delta Phi PA rolling pin (UA2001-11)
  - Town Girls Duke necklace (president on back)
  - Beat Rutgers tag (October 9, 1920) and Duke football pin (UA98-50)
  - East Campus Dining Halls matchbox
  - Trinity College locket, June 1903
  - Pin with image of Craven hall
  - Explorers' Club stamp
  - Pin from the Vigil and two 1988 Vigil reunion buttons (UA91-69)
  - Woman's College meal ticket (UA99-27)
  - Woman's College sign-out card, 1952 (UA94-119)
  - National Educational Association pin, 1903
  - Duke pennant (paper)
  - Trinity 1924 pennant (felt)
  - Duke and Trinity pennants, including the 1942 Rose Bowl (UA94-41) (Box 14)
  - Duke vs Pitt pennants (UA2007-62)
  - Armed Forces patches from WWII worn by Duke alumni (UA83-97) (Box 15)
  - Signed Basketball game ball, from January 22, 1972 (UA93-7) (Box 16)
  - Signed Basketball from 1992 (UA98-85) (Box 17)
  - President Few's top coat and vest (UA90-56) (Box 18)
  - Flag from Ambassador Angier Biddle Duke's funeral, 1995
  - President Few's top hat (UA90-56) (Box 19)
  - Asbury Building brick (Box 20 (heavy))
  - Brick with white glaze, 1923
  - Paul B. Williams Media Center plaque (from Library)
  - Conference Room Furnished by the Class of 1965 plaque
  - Chemistry Building plaque
  - Steinway Piano Gift of the Class of 1940 of the Woman's College plaque
  - Westminster Chimes Centennial Gift of the 1939 Senior Class of the Women's College plaque
  - James B. Duke's pocket watch (UA93-22) (Box 21)
  - Alpha Delta Pi charm bracelet, pin, and other miscellaneous pins, card holder
  - Five Stone Mountain Half dollars (UA93-22)
  - Glass with Duke seal, ca. 1966 (UA2005-0032)
  - Women's Studies coffee mug, 1983-1993
  - Plastic Duke football music box (UA96-91)
  - Lilly Library coffee mug
  - Five printing plates for music: "A Song of the Sons," "Bonus, Bona, Bonum," "Flag and Sunset Bell," "O Duke, Alma Mater" (Box 22 (heavy))
  - Phi Kappa Sigma plaque presented to Hiram Earl Myers, 1962
  - American Institute of Marine Underwriters and American Merchant Marine Institute plaque presented to Duke University, 1962
  - Six small printing plates of campus images, including one with 1896 Trinity Archive staff
  - Culver Academies Athletic Hall of Fame plaque presented to Edmung M. "Eddie" Cameron (UA2002-81)
  - Saddle bags with tenuous link to Brantley York (Box 23)
  - Top hat of President Few in leather case (Box 24)
  - Printing plates of Duke scenes (Box 25 (heavy))
  - Duke University plates, 1937 (UA91-52, UA96-27) and others (Box 26)
  - Happy Birthday Terry [Sanford] hat (Box 27)
  - Pastels used on set of the Neil Simon "Broadway Bound" (UA86-101)
  - Number punches (source unknown)
  - Bayonet found in Duke Forest (UA97-40)
  - Clapper from the Duke-UNC Victory bell
  - Iain Hamilton honorary degree (UA2002-40) (Box 28)
  - James B. Duke Society Tiffany box (UA98-92)
  - Hardhat from WEL (Keohane Quad) project (Judith White UA2003-4)
  - Souvenir Hardhat used by Terry Sanford at groundbreaking ceremony for the Sanford Institute, 1992
  - Column base from Trinity College, Randolph County (UA90-110) (Box 29)
  - Piece of Duke stone
  - Duke bird house (UA2005-43)
  - Ceramic plaque of William McDougall
  - Death mask of President Few (Box 30)
  - Seals for Trinity Park School, Memorial Church Fund (1938), and Duke University
  - 19th c. bottle of water (maybe Trinity College Historical Society artifact) (Box 31)
  - Trinity College Faculty Trophy, Interclass Baseball, 1914 (2 pieces)
  - Sigma Chi B League Division Champion Trophy, 1937 (Box 32)
  - Trinity College Relay Race Trophy, 1915-1916
  - Trinity College annual field day trophy, 1911-1920, presented by the Tombs (2 pieces)
  - Trinity College seals (2) (Box 33 (heavy))
  - Doctoral robe and cap (black) (Box 34)
  - Unidentified paper and medal pin (Box 35)
  - Unidentified plate
  - Southern Conference Champions football trophy, 1936 (UA2005-42)
  - Bible presenting to Z.F. Blair by Trinity College, June 14, 1883
  - Alice Baldwin academic hoods from Duke University, University of Chicago, and Woman's College, University of North Carolina (Box 36)
  - Pi Beta Chi pledge paddle, 1951 (Box 37)
  - Cane presented to Marquis Wood
  - James B. Duke topcoat (UA2000-30) (Box 38)
  - Alice Baldwin doctoral robe
  - Artifacts removed from manuscript collections (Box 39-40)
  - Blanket from the 1939 Rose Bowl [provenance unknown, date estimated] (Box 41)
  - 50th anniversary Rose Bowl medallions (1942-1992) (2) (Box 42)
  - 50th anniversary Rose Bowl pins (buttons, 3)
  - 1942 Rose Bowl tickets (3) for Pasadena
  - 1942 Rose Bowl ticket for Durham
  - 1942 Rose Bowl ticket and side line pass [UA95-20]
  - Printing block of West Campus landscape plan
  - Navel ROTC medallion (from 2007)
  - Fantasticks T-shirt
  - Freshman dink, 1958
  - Graduate School of Business glass bowl (Box 43)
  - FOCUS 2003 T-shirt
  - Springternational 2003 T-shirt
  - Corduroy jacket with Blue Devil patch on the back,circa 1930s (UA 2009-0011) (Box 44)
  - Printing blocks of architectural drawings (UA2009-0012) (Box 45)
  - Francis Micara's Miller Bishop Trophy for the 1941 Duke Homecoming Best Freshman Stunt (UA2008-0041) (Box 46)
  - Class of 1945 Dink, donor: Capt. Francis Micara (bucket hat style) (UA2008-0063) (Box 47)
  - Wedgwood Plates (UA2008-0035) (Box 48)
  - Doonesbury Cartoon (framed)(UA2008-0035) (Box 49)
  - 1938 Commemorative Towel and undated sign that says "Please keep off the grass" in French [A94-76] (Box 50)
  - 2006 "Violence is NOT a Duke Value" button (UA 2009-0033)
  - Fall 2009 Football season buttons produced by Duke University Libraries (UA2009-0033)
  - Embosser: Duke Latin motto around the perimeter, cross/ivy in the center (just over 1 inch in diameter) (Box 51)
  - Embosser: Woman's College Library/Durham, N.C. around the perimeter, Duke University in the center (Box 52)
  - Embosser: Memorial Church Fund, Inc. around the perimeter, "Corporate Seal 1926 Delaware" in the center (Box 53)
  - Trinity Park School around the perimeter, cross and books with Latin in the center emblem (Box 54)
  - Duke Latin motto around the perimeter, cross/ivy in the center (aroun 3/4 inch in diameter) (Box 55)
  - Duke Latin motto around the perimeter, cross/ivy in center (just over 1.5 inches in diameter) (Box 56)
  - Blue Devil Doll (Box 57)
  - Emily Johnson Headstone, 1895 (Box 58)
  - James B. Duke's Shaving Mug/Brush and Shoehorn; Bull Durham Tobacco Pouch and Rolling Papers (Box 59)
  - James B. Duke's Metal Cash Box (Box 60)
  - "Go to Hell Carolina" Banner, flown at 1979 graduation ceremony (Box 61)
  - Gustavino tile (UA2002-70) (Box UAV320F)
  - Bust of Deryl Hart (removed from the Hart Reading Room) (Box UAV320F)